<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fuller relation from Bridgewater since the last fight: wherein is declared the fierce and terrible storming of the town, by firing it in three severall places, and the necessity thereof: / sent to the Honorable, William Lenthall Esq; Speaker to the House of Commons. By a worthy gentleman in Sir Tho: Fairfax his army. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>Worthy Gentleman in Sir Thomas Fairfax His Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E293_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860979</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E293[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fuller relation from Bridgewater since the last fight: wherein is declared the fierce and terrible storming of the town, by firing it in three severall places, and the necessity thereof: / sent to the Honorable, William Lenthall Esq; Speaker to the House of Commons. By a worthy gentleman in Sir Tho: Fairfax his army. Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that this letter be forthwith printed and published: H: Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Worthy Gentleman in Sir Thomas Fairfax His Army.</author>
                  <author>Lenthall, William, 1591-1662.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Husband, printer to the Honourable House of Commons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iuly 26. 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bridgwater (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <p>A Fuller RELATION FROM <hi>BRIDGEWATER</hi> Since the laſt Fight: Wherein is declared the fierce and terrible ſtorming of the Town, by firing it in three ſeverall places, and the neceſsity thereof:</p>
            <p>Sent to the Honorable, <hi>William Lenthall</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Speaker to the Houſe of <hi>COMMONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a worthy Gentleman in Sir THO: FAIRFAX his Army.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>ORdered by the Commons in Parliament, That this Letter be forthwith printed and publiſhed:</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Edw. Husband,</hi> Printer to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe of Commons, Iuly 26. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113106:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113106:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>VVilliam Lenthall</hi> Eſquire, Speaker of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Writ to you formerly, of the late Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with <hi>Goring,</hi> and of the taking of <hi>Langport</hi> and <hi>Burrough,</hi> two Garriſons of the enemy; ſince which time, the Army hath blocked up <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> in nature of a Siege, and yet have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed themſelves, being neceſſitated to lie ſtill (if no Enemy had been neer) till our money came up, which arrived here on <hi>Wedneſday;</hi> and the Army Horſe and Foot being Muſtered were paid on <hi>Friday</hi> and <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> the reſt this day. But Action being moſt proper for this Army, in order to ſetling the peace of this Kingdom; the Generall in purſuance of his firſt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion moved again to ſtorm the Town (for that he was certainly informed they had Victuals, and would be a work of time to gain it) It was unanimouſly (at laſt) agreed unto, that is, to ſtorme it, this morning about two of the clock. Yeſterday being the Lords day,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113106:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
Maſter <hi>Peters</hi> in the forenoon, and Maſter <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls</hi> in the afternoon applied themſelves to the encouragement of the Souldiers on any deſigne they went about, to look upon Chriſt in all their actions, and to be valiant in his Cauſe; and about ſeven at night our Foot being drawn out, and thoſe that commanded the Storme, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne, Maſter <hi>Peters</hi> (in the field) gave them an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to do their duties, and God enabled them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: For this morning Iuly 21. about two a a clock, the Generals Regiment began the Storme, being ſeconded by others, and gave not over till they were a top of the Works with their Colours, and gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the pieces that plaid upon them, and let down the Bridge: whereupon Captain <hi>Reynolds</hi> a valiant young Gentleman, entred with a Forlorn-Hope of horſe, ſcoured the Streets, and beat them out of the hither Town into the further (our Pikes ſtanding bravely to the horſe) This poſſeſſed the enemy with that fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much perplexed at our taking the hither Town, and 500. priſoners that were part of thoſe that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the hither Works: That the Enemy for the moſt part quitted the Line on the other ſide, where we were in hope the other part with Colonell <hi>Maſsie</hi> had Stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Town, and entred; but they only gave an hot Alarme while we ſtormed (it ſeems being not then ready for it (though the time agreed on) wanting ſome neceſſaries) ſo we loſt the carrying the whole Town this time: The priſoners being brought to the Church above 500. in all with Officers; two Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonells, they aſſured they wanted not Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor Victuals, only meat for horſes and Cattell; we loſt not twenty men in the Storme, though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113106:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
in mans Iudgement, ſuch was the fierceneſſe of it, for an houre, one would not thinke leſſe then a thouſand could be ſlain; It was dark, and it ſo pleaſed God that they ſhot over for the moſt part. There was not one Officer of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te ſlaine, though many in perſon led on their men, and did gallantly, as Lieutenant Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Iackſon,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell to the Generall, and Collonel <hi>Hewſon</hi> of Collonel <hi>Pickerings</hi> Regiment. The Enemy being ſtill hardned in heart, was ſo farre from yeelding, that with Granadoes and other things, they fired that part of the town we were in, and hardly left 3. houſes ſtanding, this much inraged our men to ſee their villany, and the Generall not a little troubled to ſee a towne deſtroyed, ſummoned it once more, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Trumpet about 5. in the evening, they within were ſo peremptorie, that they would not ſo much as offer to come to a treaty, whereupon the Generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the towne to bee ſtormed on Colonell <hi>Maſsies</hi> ſide, to morrow morning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> 22. <hi>Tueſday,</hi> at the dawning of the day the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (as the night before) in perſon gave order for the forces on this ſide to give a fierce alarum with great and ſmall ſhot, while they on the other ſide fell on, which on our ſide was done with great reſolution, and but that the tide was up, we might alone have gained the Towne. They on the other ſide, againe failing to fall on, only giving an Alarum. God by his providence ſo ordering it that ſomething was wanting, and I hope in the Lord it was for the beſt, and for the preſervation of many a mans life. For this day, the hot Alarum wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nothing upon them, which indeed was almoſt a ſecond ſtorme, the Generall was enraged againſt them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113106:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
and leaſt the innocent ſhould ſuffer among the nocent, ſent a Trumpet to the Governour to let all women and children come out of the Town, by 4. a clock this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon. And accordingly, the Lady Governeſſe, (one too guilty of the miſery of that place) the Lady <hi>Hamley,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Marre,</hi> and divers others came out, this being done, our great Gunnes and Morter-peeces with fire-balls, hot Irons, &amp;c. plaid againſt the towne, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fired it in 3. places, the wind being great increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the fire, and all on a flame on a ſudden, ſuch a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror it wrought upon them, that <hi>Tom Elliot</hi> came run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out to the Generall for a parley. The Generall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, the Governour refuſed it the laſt night, and now that he had brought this miſery on himſelfe, the Generall would not admit of a Treaty, yet if he would ſubmit to mercy he ſhould have it, in the mean time till he returned a ſpeedy &amp; poſitive anſwer, if any Souldier in the Town offered to take off a ſlate on the houſe, or quench the fire, our ſouldiers eryed the ceſſation ſhould be void, and we would take all advantages, this ſo ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them that inſtantly they came out and cryed mercy for the Lords ſake, ſo it was agreed on, and quarter they have for their lives, and have liberty to ſave the towne; but as thoſe lately come out ſay, the towneſmen do not ſo faſt quench the fire, as the ſouldiers within in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of this Army, ſet it on fire in freſh places. I heard Sir <hi>Iohn Hele,</hi> Maſter <hi>Speke</hi> and other of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſay, there are about 40 p<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece of Ordnance, 40 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred weight of Match, powder proportionable, victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als for 2000. ſouldiers for 4. moneths; 500. we took the other day, above 1000. yet within; Commanders, Reformadoes, Gentlemen, and fat Prieſts, its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113106:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
above 200. Treaſure in Plate, Iewels, &amp;c. ſaid to be worth 100000 .l. but all will be conſumed with fire, we doubt: The workes of the towne are as ſtrong, as any in <hi>England,</hi> the moat deepe, yet our foote waded through, all the bridges failing but one, and ſo got o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: It was about 30. foote wide, the Bearer ſee the ſtorme, and the Towne on fire, be pleaſed to move for his paines.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iuly 22. twelve at night.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iulii 25. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, That this Letter concerning the taking of <hi>Bridgewater</hi> be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
